At first, "it" was a sphere.
เเรกเริ่ม "เจ้าสิ่งนั้น" เป็นลูกบอลลูกหนึ่ง
Not just any normal sphere.
แต่ว่าไม่ใช่ลูกบอลธรรมดา
"It" could change itself by imitating all that may and does exist.
มันสามารถเลียนแบบและเปลี่ยนเป็นสิ่งนั้นได้
I decided to place "it" upon this land
ฉันโยน "เจ้าสิ่งนั้น" ลงมาบนพื้นแผ่นดินนี้
and observe it.
แล้วก็จับตาดู
For some time, it assumed the form of a rock.
มันเปลี่ยนเป็นก้อนหินอยู่พักหนึ่ง
When temperatures rose,
เมื่ออากาศอบอุ่น
it copied the appearance of moss.
มันก็กลายเปลี่ยนเป็นตะไคร่น้ำ
Before long, snow began to fall upon this land.
ไม่ช้า ก็จะเริ่มมีหิมะตกลงมาบนพื้นแผ่นดินนี้
A single wolf came ambling from the south,
หมาป่าตัวหนึ่งเดินมาจากทางใต้
and once it tired...
หมดแรงล้มตัวลง
"It" took the form of an animal...
เจ้าสิ่งนั้นได้เปลี่ยนร่างเป็นหมาป่า
and gained consciousness.
มันเริ่มมีจิตใต้สำนึก
It did not know how to move or where to go,
เริ่มแรกมันไม่รู้ว่าต้องเดินยังไง
but it picked up the wolf's habits instantly.
แต่ก็เรียนรู้ได้ไว
Its movements were slow.
เคลื่อนไหวยังไม่กระฉับกระเฉง
Evidently, it had copied the injured wolf's wounds as well...
ดูเหมือนว่าแม้แต่บาดแผลก็เลียนแบบมาด้วย
Its initial discomfort...
ครั้งแรกที่รู้สึกไม่สบาย
and its initial pain...
ครั้งแรกที่รู้สึกเจ็บปวด
healed within 20 seconds.
แต่พอผ่านไป 20 วินาทีบาดแผลก็หายสนิท
And it continued on without issue.
ไม่มีปัญหาอะไร
"It" began to walk.
"เจ้าสิ่งนั้น" ก็เริ่มออกเดิน
Carving into its mind, the frostiness of the wind and the smell of the snow.
จดจำความหนาวเหน็บของสายลมและกลิ่นของหิมะเป็นครั้งแรก
Yet, it had no destination.
เดินอย่างไร้จุดหมาย
TO YOUR ETERNITY
แด่เธอผู้เป็นนิรันดร์
Joan! You're finally back!
โจอัน กลับมาแล้วเหรอ
I'm so glad you're safe!
ดีจริง ๆ ที่ปลอดภัย
You've been gone for two months. I was so worried!
หายไปตั้งสองเดือน ฉันเป็นห่วงแทบแย่
I knew you wouldn't forget about me!
ฉันรู้ว่านายไม่มีทางลืมฉันอยู่แล้ว
You seem quieter than usual.
นายดูเชื่องกว่าแต่ก่อนนะ
I know. You must be tired.
เข้าใจละ นายคงเหนื่อยสินะ
There were many unfamiliar things there.
ที่นั่นมีสิ่งที่มันไม่รู้จักมากมาย
The comfort of warmth...
อุณหภูมิในร่างกายเพิ่มขึ้นจนรู้สึกสบาย
and unknown fragrances.
กับได้กลิ่นหอมจากของบางอย่างที่ไม่รู้จัก
This place was enchanting.
ช่างเป็นบรรยากาศที่ชวนให้หลงใหล
If it could speak, it would probably say,
หากว่าพูดได้
"I want to stay here forever."
คงจะพูดว่า "อยากอยู่ที่นี่ตลอดไป"
I'm always telling you not to get too close to the fire.
ฉันเตือนอยู่บ่อย ๆ ว่าไม่ให้เข้าใกล้ไฟ
Here's your food.
มา กินข้าว
Here.
กินสิ
Hm?
แปลกจัง
I see. This isn't caribou milk.
เข้าใจแล้ว คงไม่ชอบกินสินะ
You must not like it.
เพราะว่าไม่ใช่นมกวางสินะ
Well, there's no helping it.
ช่วยไม่ได้นี่นา
The last caribou died a year ago...
กวางตัวสุดท้ายตายไปตั้งปีหนึ่งแล้วนี่
The fire will go out soon.
ไฟใกล้ดับแล้ว
Let's sleep before it gets cold.
รีบนอนก่อนที่อากาศจะเย็นดีกว่า
That nameless boy
เด็กหนุ่มที่ไม่รู้จักชื่อคนนี้
was the first human "it" met.
คือคนคนแรกที่เจ้าสิ่งนั้นได้พบ
"Episode 1: THE FINAL ONE"
ตอนที่ 1 คนสุดท้าย
After it snows, it's hard to get dry stuff.
หิมะตกไม่หยุด ไม้ชื้นหมดเลย
We can't use the wood at my aunt's place.
ไม้ที่บ้านคุณป้าก็ใช้ไม่ได้
It's like we're borrowing from people's houses. Isn't that something?
นายจะบอกว่าฉันไม่ควรหยิบของจากบ้านคนอื่นใช่ไหม
I'm sorry. I know it well.
ขอโทษนะ ฉันรู้แล้วล่ะ
If they came back, they'd probably be angry...
ทุกคนกลับมาต้องด่าฉันเละแน่เลย
Well, it can't be helped!
ช่วยไม่ได้นี่นา
If I don't do this, I'll die!
ถ้าไม่ทำแบบนี้ ฉันหนาวตายแน่
Of course, they will!
แน่นอน...
It's only been five years since they left! Only five years!
ทุกคนไปจากที่นี่ตั้งห้าปีแล้ว ห้าปีแล้ว
They left for a place far away...
เพราะฟากนั้น
Far beyond the horizon,
ฟากที่อยู่ไกล ๆ นั่น
believing that there,
มีผู้คนและอาหารเยอะมาก
they would find people and food.
ทุกคนล้วนเชื่ออย่างนั้น
According to them, that place is like a paradise.
ทุกคนบอกว่าที่นั่นเหมือนสวรรค์
There are lots of fish
ได้ยินมาว่ามีปลาเยอะ
and even something they call "fruit".
แล้วก็มีสิ่งที่เรียกว่า "ผลไม้" อยู่มาก
There are people far smarter than us
คนที่นั่นฉลาดกว่าพวกเราตั้งเยอะ
who live happily every day.
ใช้ชีวิตมีความสุขอยู่ทุก ๆ วัน
How nice... I would've liked to go.
ดีจัง ฉันก็อยากไปเหมือนกัน
Remember?
นายยังจำได้ไหม
I was trying to sneak out with all the adults,
เมื่อก่อนตอนที่ฉันจะไปกับพวกผู้ใหญ่
but you stopped me from going.
ถูกนายรั้งไว้ เลยอดไปเลย
By biting my leg!
ตอนนั้นนายงับขาฉันไว้ไงล่ะ
Then, they told me, "You stay here! Look after the elderly!"
ทุกคนให้ฉันอยู่เฝ้าบ้านเลยบอกว่า "แกดูแลคนแก่ด้วยล่ะ"
That was so mean...
ไม่ไหวเลยนะ
They said they'd come back with souvenirs if they found that place...
ก็บอกเองแท้ ๆ ว่าเจอที่นั่นแล้วจะเอาของกลับมาฝาก
They did say that, right?
ทั้งที่บอกเองแท้ ๆ
In the end, the ones left behind...
สุดท้ายที่นี่ก็เหลือแค่ฉัน
were the elderly I couldn't save...
ที่ช่วยคนแก่ไว้ไม่ได้
and the two of us...
และพวกเรา
Joan!
โจอัน
Please...
ขอร้องล่ะ
Welcome back...
ยินดีตอนรับกลับมา
What a surprise! It's a fish!
อะไรกัน ปลาหรอกเหรอ
Hooray! What a big catch!
ดีจัง ไม่ได้จับปลาตัวใหญ่เบ้อเริ่มแบบนี้มานานแล้ว
Here, this is for you.
เอ้า นี่ของนาย
To save fuel,
ต้องประหยัดฟืน
let's eat this raw.
กินสด ๆ เลยแล้วกัน
Why won't you eat it?
ทำไมล่ะ นายชอบไม่ใช่เหรอ
Did you forget how?
ลืมวิธีการกินเหรอ
Here...
ดูนะ
Like this...
แบบนี้
With your mouth... Chew it...
ใช้ปากกัด แล้วก็เคี้ยว ๆ
Here!
ดูสิ
Here.
เอ้า
Well, you can eat it after all.
เอ้า นายก็กินได้นี่
These are aunty and uncle.
นี่คือลุงและป้า
My cousin and his children.
นี่พี่ชายและลูก ๆ ของเขา
And the uncle with a beard down the road.
คุณปู่หนวดเฟิ้มที่อยู่ตรงข้ามบ้านเรา
This is the aunty next door.
นี่คุณป้าที่อยู่ข้าง ๆ บ้าน
It looks like her, doesn't it?
เหมือนใช่ไหม
So that there's evidence that people were here...
ที่ทำแบบนี้ก็เพื่อให้รู้ว่านี่คือคนที่เคยอยู่ที่นี่
And so I that I don't forget.
และเพื่อไม่ลืมน่ะ
Joan.
โจอัน
I'm thinking of leaving this place.
ฉันว่าจะไปจากที่นี่แล้วเหมือนกัน
I want to meet new people
ฉันอยากรู้จักผู้คนมากกว่านี้
and have new experiences.
อยากเจอเรื่องราวต่าง ๆ
Surely there'll be some bad things mixed in,
อาจจะเจอเรื่องร้าย ๆ
but I want to see the world.
แต่ถึงอย่างนั้น ฉันก็ยังอยากเข้าใจโลกใบนี้อยู่ดี
With you, of course.
แน่นอนว่า นายก็ต้องไปกับฉันด้วยเหมือนกัน
I can't even see the sea anymore!
มองไม่เห็นทะเลแล้ว
It's my first time coming this far out.
ฉันมาที่นี่เป็นครั้งแรก
Uncle said it was...
ตามที่คุณลุงพูดไว้
directly south.
ต้องไปทางทิศใต้
Just walk straight ahead from the house.
หันหลังให้บ้านแล้วเดินตรงไป
You can't see it in these conditions,
แม้ว่าตอนนี้จะยังไม่เห็น
but eventually, a big wall-like mountain will appear.
แต่ว่าเดินไปเรื่อย ๆ จะเห็นภูเขาเหมือนกำแพงขนาดใหญ่
Beyond that is paradise.
ข้ามไปก็จะเป็นสวรรค์
Well, let's go further before it gets dark!
เอาละ เราเดินไปจนกว่าจะมืดเลยแล้วกัน
What is that?
นั่นคืออะไร
It's a message!
ข้อความนี่
For people like us who are searching for that paradise!
เหมือนว่าจะมีไว้ให้คนที่จะมุ่งหน้าไปสวรรค์แบบเรา
It says to go this way!
ให้ฉันตรงไปทางนี้สินะ
Awesome!
เยี่ยมไปเลย
This is such a relief!
ดีจริง ๆ
Joan, coming here was worth it!
โจอัน คิดถูกสินะที่ออกมา
I'm happy too!
ใช่ไหมล่ะ ฉันก็ดีใจมากเหมือนกัน
Joan, have you ever heard of "vegetables"?
โจอัน นายรู้ไหมว่าอะไรคือผัก
Apparently, I've had them before, but I can't remember at all.
เหมือนว่าเมื่อก่อนฉันเคยกินแหละ
And sweet, round "fruits"!
ยังมีผลไม้ลูกกลม ๆ หวาน ๆ
I don't know what "sweet" tastes like,
รสชาติหวานเป็นยังไง
so I asked uncle, but he couldn't really explain it either.
เคยถามคุณลุงแล้วแต่ฉันก็ยังไม่ค่อยเข้าใจ
I'd like to try it soon.
อยากกินเร็ว ๆ จัง
I can't wait...
ตื่นเต้นจังเลย
Freedom feels great!
ความรู้สึกได้เป็นอิสระมันดีมากเลย
It's starting to snow...
หิมะตกแล้ว
Is that a complaint I hear, Joan?
เมื่อกี้ถอนหายใจเหรอ โจอัน
The journey has only just started!
การเดินทางเพิ่งเริ่มเองนะ
Look! A tree!
นายดูสิ ต้นไม้
Amazing! This is proof we're getting closer to the mountains!
เจ๋งไปเลย หมายความว่าเราเข้าใกล้ภูเขาแล้ว
We can use some of this as fuel!
เก็บไปใช้เป็นฟืนดีกว่า
All right!
ดี
Let's resume our journey!
ออกเดินทางกันต่อ
Ah, that was embarrassing!
แย่จัง
My face is freezing!
หน้าจะแข็งแล้ว
I'm completely soaked!
เปียกไปหมด
But it's amazing!
แต่ว่ายอดไปเลย
To think there'd be a river here!
ไม่คิดว่าตรงนี้จะมีแม่น้ำด้วย
Let's fish!
มาตกปลากันเถอะ
You were smiling just now, weren't you?
เมื่อกี้นายหัวเราะเหรอ
There. That'll do.
แค่นี้ก็เรียบร้อย
It's fine. Don't worry.
ไม่เป็นไร นายไม่ต้องห่วง
It's just a flesh wound.
แค่แผลถลอกเอง
Hey, don't joke around.
อย่าล้อเล่นน่า
I'm not going back.
ฉันไม่กลับไปหรอก
I can't do something that uncool.
ฉันไม่ทำเรื่องหน้าอายแบบนั้นหรอก
And we still have plenty of food.
เสบียงยังไม่หมดนะ
Let's keep going tomorrow.
พรุ่งนี้ค่อยเดินทางต่อ
The day after tomorrow and the day after that,
มะรืนและวันต่อ ๆ ไป
I'll keep walking, even if you complain!
ต่อให้นายไม่อยากไป ฉันก็จะไป
As long as I have strength, I'll keep going!
ตราบใดที่มีแรงฉันจะเดินต่อไป
That's not right, Joan.
นายผิดแล้ว โจอัน
To stop going further because we don't know if they're alive...
เพราะว่าไม่รู้ว่าทุกคนจะเป็นตายร้ายดียังไง จะให้หยุดเดินงั้นเหรอ
is even more foolish.
ฉันคิดว่าทำแบบนั้นโง่กว่าอีก
If we return, we'll only rot away in that house.
กลับไปก็แค่ผุพังไปพร้อมกับบ้านหลังนั้น
I can't accept that!
แบบนั้นฉันไม่เอาหรอก
I will go to where they all have gone!
ตอนนี้ฉันคิดแค่เรื่องเดียว
I have nothing else to do but that!
ว่าจะไปที่เดียวกับทุก ๆ คน
The fact that they haven't returned
อีกอย่างที่ทุกคนยังไม่กลับมา
surely means that paradise is too fascinating!
ต้องเป็นเพราะที่นั่นน่าหลงใหลแน่ ๆ เลย
It's because they're enjoying it so much...
มีของกินที่น่าหลงไหลและเต็มไปด้วยเสน่ห์ของผู้คน
The fascinating food and the fascinating people...
พวกเขาใช้ชีวิตอย่างมีความสุขจนลืมบ้านเกิด
That's why...
ดังนั้น...
This is amazing, Joan!
โจอัน นายนี่ยอดไปเลย
These are the remains of people!
นี่เป็นร่องรอยว่ามีคนเคยมาที่นี่
Look at this!
นายรีบมาดูสิ
This means that everyone made it this far!
แสดงว่าทุกคนเคยอยู่ที่นี่
That's why...
เพราะฉะนั้น...
For sure, ahead of us...
สวรรค์จะต้องอยู่ข้างหน้าแน่ ๆ
is the way to the mountains!
เดินต่อไปก็จะถึงภูเขาลูกนั้น
We can definitely make it!
เราจะต้องไปถึงแน่
We can make it...
ต้องไปถึงแน่...
Can we... make it?
ถึงแน่...
What do you think, Joan?
นายว่าไง โจอัน
Do you think we can make it?
นายว่าฉันจะเดินไปถึงไหม
Tell me!
บอกฉันมาสิ
Say something... Like you always do...
เหมือนกับที่นายบอกฉันอยู่บ่อย ๆ ไง
That's right... You can't reply...
ใช่สิ นายจะตอบฉันได้ยังไง
That's right... Isn't it?
จริง ๆ แล้ว
I've only been talking to myself all along...
เป็นฉันที่พูดกับตัวเองมาโดยตลอด
Curse it! Curse it all!
บัดซบ บัดซบ
That's right...
จริงสิ...
I'm sorry, Joan.
ขอโทษนะ โจอัน
Even though you've been with me for so long...
นายอยู่ข้างฉันมาโดยตลอด
I'm saying... these things...
แต่ฉันกลับพูดแบบนี้
Sorry... I'm sorry...
ขอโทษ ขอโทษ...
Let's go back...
พวกเรากลับกันเถอะ
Let's go back, Joan.
พวกเรากลับหันเถอะ โจอัน
I've decided...
ฉันตัดสินใจแล้ว
It's not your fault... I want to go back...
ไม่ใช่นายหรอก เป็นฉันต่างหากที่อยากกลับ
I want to go back...
ฉันอยากกลับไป
Let's go back.
กลับกันเถอะ
What's with that face?
ทำหน้าอะไรของนาย
Are you not feeling well?
ไม่สบายเหรอ
Or are you trying to make me laugh?
หรือว่าหัวเราะเยาะฉัน
I know, I know.
เข้าใจแล้ว
You must be hungry.
นายหิวใช่ไหม
I'll prepare some food.
ฉันจะทำอาหารให้กินเดี๋ยวนี้แหละ
It's healing.
โอเคขึ้นแล้ว แผลเริ่มดีขึ้นแล้ว
Does it smell nice?
นายว่ามันกลิ่นหอมน่ากินเหรอ
Once this heals,
ไว้แผลฉันหายก่อน
let's challenge ourselves again, Joan!
ค่อยไปพิชิตกันใหม่นะ โจอัน
That's weird...
แปลกจัง..
Chair...
เก้าอี้...
You see...
นายดูสิ
If... If I'm sleeping when they all come back...
ถ้าทุกคนกลับมา
That would be embarrassing, right?
เห็นฉันนอนบนเตียง ไม่ได้เรื่องเลยใช่ไหมล่ะ
Determination...
นี่คือความมุ่งมั่นของฉัน
is what...
นั่งบนนี้...
makes me cool.
ค่อยเหมาะหน่อย
Joan... I...
โจอัน ฉัน...
have a request to make of you.
มีเรื่องอยากจะขอร้องนาย
Don't ever...
ช่วยจำ...
forget about me.
เรื่องฉันไว้ตลอดไปด้วยนะ...
All right! Let's head out to paradise one more time!
เอาละ มุ่งหน้าไปสวรรค์ต่อกันเถอะ
Joan!
โจอัน
Everyone!
ทุกคนอยู่ที่นี่หมด
They were all waiting for me.
อย่างนี้เหรอ ทุกคนกำลังรอฉันเหรอ
I won't be alone anymore.
ยอดไปเลย ฉันไม่ได้อยู่คนเดียวแล้ว
Now I can do my best!
แบบนี้ฉันก็สู้ต่อไปได้แล้วล่ะ
Look, everyone! There are people up ahead!
ทุกคนดูนั่น ข้างหน้ามีคน
Hello.
สวัสดีครับทุกคน
It's nice to meet you.
ยินดีที่ได้รู้จักครับ
What kind of place is this?
ที่นี่คือที่ไหนเหรอครับ
Do you know about something called "fruit"?
รู้จักผลไม้หรือเปล่าครับ
Hello, nice to meet you!
ยินดีที่ได้รู้จักครับ สวัสดีครับ
My name is...
ผมชื่อ...
Thus...
ดังนั้น
"It" acquired the form of a human.
"เจ้าสิ่งนั้น" ได้ร่างมนุษย์มา
There are conditions to this transformation.
แต่เงื่อนไขที่ได้มาก็คือ...
There must be an "impetus".
"แรงกระตุ้น"
And so it set out to seek an even stronger stimulus.
เพื่อตามหาแรงกระตุ้นให้มากกว่านี้จึงก้าวเดินออกมา
It will likely meet all sorts of people
นับจากนี้เจ้าสิ่งนั้นจะได้รู้จักกับคนมากมาย
and have all kinds of experiences,
ได้สัมผัสกับเรื่องราวต่าง ๆ
just as the boy wished.
เหมือนกับที่เด็กหนุ่มเคยอยากจะลอง
"It" arrives in the land of Ninannah.
"เจ้าสิ่งนั้น" มาถึงป่าใหญ่นินันนา
March, a girl raised in the village
เด็กหญิงมาชิถูกเลี้ยงในชนบท
was selected as a sacrifice.
มาชิถูกเลือกเป็นของเซ่นไหว้ของหมู่บ้าน
Her dream of becoming an adult was thus shattered.
ความฝันที่จะกลายเป็นผู้ใหญ่ของเธอดับสลาย
To survive,
เพื่อให้มีชีวิตอยู่ต่อ
"Episode 2 THE DISOBEDIENT GIRL" the two lives intertwine.
"ตอนที่ 2 เด็กหญิงที่ไม่เชื่อฟัง" ทั้งสองชีวิตจึงได้พบกัน